I want you to imagine
أريد منكم التخيل
walking into a room,
أنكم تدخلون إلى غرفة،
a control room with a bunch of people,
غرفة تحكم فيها مجموعة من الأشخاص،
a hundred people, hunched over a desk with little dials,
مئات الأشخاص المنحنين فوق مكتب به أقراص صغيرة،
and that that control room
وغرفة التحكم تلك
will shape the thoughts and feelings
تشكّل أفكار ومشاعر
of a billion people.
مليارات الأشخاص.
This might sound like science fiction,
قد يبدو هذا مثل الخيال العلمي،
but this actually exists
لكن هذا يحدث بالفعل
right now, today.
الآن، اليوم.
I know because I used to be in one of those control rooms.
أعلم هذا لأنني كنت في غرف التحكم هذه.
I was a design ethicist at Google,
كنت مصمم أخلاقيات في جوجل،
where I studied how do you ethically steer people's thoughts?
حيث درست كيفية توجيه أفكار الناس أخلاقيًا؟
Because what we don't talk about is how the handful of people
لأن ما لا نتحدث عنه هو كيف لمجموعة صغيرة
working at a handful of technology companies
من الذين يعملون في شركات تكنولوجية معدودة
through their choices will steer what a billion people are thinking today.
وتبعًا لاختياراتهم سيوجّهون تفكير مليارات الأشخاص اليوم.
Because when you pull out your phone
لأنه عندما تلتقط هاتفك
and they design how this works or what's on the feed,
ويصممون طريقة عمل هذا، أو المتابعات الإخبارية،
it's scheduling little blocks of time in our minds.
فإنه يجدول فترات زمنية قليلة في عقولنا.
If you see a notification, it schedules you to have thoughts
إذا رأيت إشعارًا، فإنه يجدولك لتكتسب أفكار
that maybe you didn't intend to have.
ربما لم تكن تنوي اكتسابها.
If you swipe over that notification,
إذا تابعت هذا الإشعار،
it schedules you into spending a little bit of time
فإنه يجدولك لتقضي فترة زمنية قصيرة
getting sucked into something
وأنت منجذب لشيء ما
that maybe you didn't intend to get sucked into.
ربما لم تكن تنوي أن يكون من اهتمامك.
When we talk about technology,
عندما نتحدث عن التكنولوجيا،
we tend to talk about it as this blue sky opportunity.
فإننا نميل للتحدث عنها وكأنها فرصة خيالية
It could go any direction.
ويمكن أن تسير في أي اتجاه.
And I want to get serious for a moment
وأنا أريد أن آخذ الأمر بجدية للحظة
and tell you why it's going in a very specific direction.
وأخبركم لماذا تسير نحو اتجاه معين.
Because it's not evolving randomly.
لأنها لا تتطور عشوائيًا.
There's a hidden goal driving the direction
هناك هدف مخفي يقود الاتجاه
of all of the technology we make,
الخاص بالتكنولوجيا التي نصنعها،
and that goal is the race for our attention.
وهذا الهدف هو السباق نحو جذب الانتباه.
Because every news site,
لأن كل موقع جديد،
TED, elections, politicians,
مثل (TED) والانتخابات والسياسيين،
games, even meditation apps
والألعاب وحتى تطبيقات اليوجا،
have to compete for one thing,
تتنافس كلها حول شيء واحد،
which is our attention,
ألا وهو جذب اهتمامنا،
and there's only so much of it.
وهناك الكثير منه.
And the best way to get people's attention
وأفضل طريقة للحصول على اهتمام الناس
is to know how someone's mind works.
هي معرفة طريقة تفكير شخص ما.
And there's a whole bunch of persuasive techniques
وهناك مجموعة كبيرة من الطرق المقنعة
that I learned in college at a lab called the Persuasive Technology Lab
التي تعلمتها في الجامعة في مختبر يدعى (مختبر تكنولوجيا الإقناع)
to get people's attention.
لجذب اهتمام الناس.
A simple example is YouTube.
مثال بسيط وهو موقع (يوتيوب).
YouTube wants to maximize how much time you spend.
يريد (يوتيوب) زيادة الوقت الذي تمضيه في المشاهدة.
And so what do they do?
فماذا يفعلون؟
They autoplay the next video.
يشغلون الفيديو التالي تلقائيًا.
And let's say that works really well.
دعونا ندّعي أن هذا فعال للغاية.
They're getting a little bit more of people's time.
لقد استطاعوا زيادة الوقت الذي يمضيه الناس قليلًا.
Well, if you're Netflix, you look at that and say,
حسنًا، لو أنك شركة (نيتفلكس)، فستنظر وتقول،
well, that's shrinking my market share,
هذا يقلل حصتي في السوق،
But then if you're Facebook,
ولكن إن كنت شركة (فيسبوك)،
you say, that's shrinking all of my market share,
ستقول أن هذا يقلص كل حصصي في السوق،
so now I have to autoplay all the videos in the newsfeed
لذلك لابد من تشغيل جميع الفيديوهات في الصفحة الرئيسية
before waiting for you to click play.
قبل أن تضغطوا على زر التشغيل.
So the internet is not evolving at random.
لذلك لا تتطور شبكة (الإنترنت) عشوائيًا.
The reason it feels like it's sucking us in the way it is
والسبب في إحساسنا أنه يجذبنا بهذه الطريقة
is because of this race for attention.
هو هذا السباق على جذب اهتمامنا.
We know where this is going.
نحن نعلم نتيجة هذا.
Technology is not neutral,
التكنولوجيا ليست حيادية،
and it becomes this race to the bottom of the brain stem
وقد أصبحت سباق إلى دماغ الإنسان
of who can go lower to get it.
ومن يستطيع التعمق للحصول عليه.
Let me give you an example of Snapchat.
دعوني أعطيكم مثالًا عن (سناب شات).
If you didn't know, Snapchat is the number one way
إن كنتم لا تعلمون، (سناب شات) هو الوسيلة الأولى
that teenagers in the United States communicate.
التي يتواصل بها المراهقون في الولايات المتحدة .
So if you're like me, and you use text messages to communicate,
فإذا كنتم مثلي تستخدمون الرسائل النصية للتواصل،
Snapchat is that for teenagers,
فإن (سناب شات) من أجل المراهقين،
and there's, like, a hundred million of them that use it.
ويستخدمه مئات الملايين منهم.
And they invented a feature called Snapstreaks,
واخترعوا خاصية اسمها (سناب ستريكس)،
which shows the number of days in a row
والتي تُظهر عدد الأيام المتتالية
that two people have communicated with each other.
التي يتواصل فيها شخصان مع بعضهما.
In other words, what they just did
وبمعنى آخر فإن ما فعلوه
is they gave two people something they don't want to lose.
هو أنهم منحوا شخصين شيئًا لا يريدان خسارته.
Because if you're a teenager, and you have 150 days in a row,
لأنك إذا كنت مراهقًا وتملك 150 يومًا متتاليًا،
you don't want that to go away.
فأنت لا تريد أن يذهب هذا هباءً.
And so think of the little blocks of time that that schedules in kids' minds.
لذا فكروا في هذه الفترات الزمنية الصغيرة التي تستحوذ على عقول الصغار.
This isn't theoretical: when kids go on vacation,
هذا ليس كلام نظري: عنما يذهب الصغار في عطلة،
it's been shown they give their passwords to up to five other friends
فقد ظهر أنهم يعطون كلمة المرور إلى 5 أصدقاء لهم
to keep their Snapstreaks going,
لكي يستمروا في (سناب ستريكس)،
even when they can't do it.
حتى وإن كانوا مشغولين.
And they have, like, 30 of these things,
ويمتلكون 30 من هذه الأشياء،
and so they have to get through taking photos of just pictures or walls
وعليهم أن يستخدموها من خلال التقاط الصور أو حتى الحائط
or ceilings just to get through their day.
أو السقف لتمضية يومهم.
So it's not even like they're having real conversations.
وهذا ليس مثل إجراء محادثات حقيقية.
We have a temptation to think about this
لدينا ميول لنفكر بهذا
as, oh, they're just using Snapchat
على أنهم يستخدمون (سناب شات) فحسب
the way we used to gossip on the telephone.
كما اعتدنا الثرثرة على الهاتف.
It's probably OK.
وتقولون أن هذا مقبول.
Well, what this misses is that in the 1970s,
حسنًا، ما يفقده هذا أنه في السبعينات،
when you were just gossiping on the telephone,
عندما كنت تثرثر على الهاتف،
there wasn't a hundred engineers on the other side of the screen
لم يكن هناك مئات المهندسين على الناحية الأخرى من الشاشة
who knew exactly how your psychology worked
الذين يعلمون تمامًا كيف تعمل نفسيتكم
and orchestrated you into a double bind with each other.
وينسقون لكم التزام ثنائي مشترك مع بعضكم البعض.
Now, if this is making you feel a little bit of outrage,
إذا كان هذا يشعركم بالغضب قليلًا،
notice that that thought just comes over you.
لاحظوا أن هذه الفكرة قد راودتكم الآن.
Outrage is a really good way also of getting your attention,
يعد الغضب أيضًا وسيلة جيدة لجذب الانتباه،
because we don't choose outrage.
لأننا لا نختار الغضب،
It happens to us.
لكنه يحدث لنا.
And if you're the Facebook newsfeed,
وإذا كنتم مسؤولين عن الأخبار في (فيسبوك)،
whether you'd want to or not,
سواء أردتم ذلك أم لا،
you actually benefit when there's outrage.
في الواقع ستستفيدون من الغضب.
Because outrage doesn't just schedule a reaction
لأن الغضب لا يجدول فقط رد الفعل
in emotional time, space, for you.
في الأوقات العاطفية والمساحة الخاصة بكم.
We want to share that outrage with other people.
نحن نريد مشاركة الغضب مع الأشخاص الآخرين.
So we want to hit share and say,
لذلك نضغط على "مشاركة" ونقول،
"Can you believe the thing that they said?"
" هل تصدقون الأمور التي قالوها؟"
And so outrage works really well at getting attention,
لذلك للغضب فاعلية شديدة في جذب الانتباه،
such that if Facebook had a choice between showing you the outrage feed
لدرجة أنه إذا اختار (فيسبوك) بين إظهار الأخبار التي تبعث على الغضب
and a calm newsfeed,
أو الأخبار الهادئة،
they would want to show you the outrage feed,
سيختاروا عرض الأخبار الباعثة على الغضب،
not because someone consciously chose that,
ليس لأن شخصًا ما اختار ذلك عن قصد،
but because that worked better at getting your attention.
لكن لأن ذلك هو الأفضل لجذب انتباهك.
And the newsfeed control room is not accountable to us.
وغرفة التحكم في تزويد الأخبار ليست مسؤولة أمامنا.
It's only accountable to maximizing attention.
تعتبر مسؤولة فقط لزيادة الانتباه.
It's also accountable,
كما أنها مسؤولة،
because of the business model of advertising,
بسبب النموذج التجاري للإعلانات،
for anybody who can pay the most to actually walk into the control room
ويتاح للأشخاص القادرين أكثر على الدفع الدخول بالفعل إلى غرفة التحكم
and say, "That group over there,
ويقولون: " تلك المجموعة هناك،
I want to schedule these thoughts into their minds."
نريد جدولة هذه الأفكار في عقولهم."
So you can target,
حيث يمكنكم السعي وراء،
you can precisely target a lie
يمكنكم بالتحديد السعي وراء كذبة
directly to the people who are most susceptible.
مباشرةً للأشخاص الذين يتأثرون بسرعة.
And because this is profitable, it's only going to get worse.
ولأن ذلك الأمر مربح سيصبح أسوأ.
So I'm here today
لذلك أنا هنا اليوم
because the costs are so obvious.
لأن التكاليف واضحة للغاية.
I don't know a more urgent problem than this,
لا أعرف مشكلة ملحّة أكثر من هذه،
because this problem is underneath all other problems.
لأن هذه المشكلة تختبيء تحت كل هذه المشاكل.
It's not just taking away our agency
لا تستحوذ فقط على حريتنا
to spend our attention and live the lives that we want,
لننجذب للأشياء التي نريدها ونعيش حياتنا كما نرغب،
it's changing the way that we have our conversations,
إنها تغير الطريقة التي نتحاور بها،
it's changing our democracy,
إنها تغير الديمقراطية الخاصة بنا،
and it's changing our ability to have the conversations
وتغير قدرتنا على الحوار
and relationships we want with each other.
والعلاقات التي نرغب بها مع بعضنا البعض.
And it affects everyone,
كما أنها تؤثر علينا جميعًا،
because a billion people have one of these in their pocket.
لأن مليار شخص لديهم جهاز كهذا في جيوبهم.
So how do we fix this?
كيف بإمكاننا إصلاح ذلك؟
We need to make three radical changes
يجب علينا إجراء ثلاثة تغيرات جذرية
to technology and to our society.
للتكنولوجيا والمجتمع الخاص بنا.
The first is we need to acknowledge that we are persuadable.
أولًا علينا الاعتراف بأننا قابلون للإقناع.
Once you start understanding
بمجرد أن تبدأوا باستيعاب
that your mind can be scheduled into having little thoughts
أن دماغكم من الممكن جدولته ليحتوي أفكار صغيرة
or little blocks of time that you didn't choose,
أو مساحات زمنية صغيرة لم تختاروها،
wouldn't we want to use that understanding
لمَ لا نرغب في توظيف هذا الفهم
and protect against the way that that happens?
والحماية من أسباب حدوث ذلك؟
I think we need to see ourselves fundamentally in a new way.
أعتقد أننا نحتاج لرؤية أنفسنا أساسًا بشكل جديد.
It's almost like a new period of human history,
إنه أمر مماثل لحقبة جديدة في تاريخ الإنسانية،
like the Enlightenment,
شيء يشبه عصر التنوير،
but almost a kind of self-aware Enlightenment,
لكنه نوعًا ما مثل تنوير الوعي بالذات،
that we can be persuaded,
أنه يمكن إقناعنا،
and there might be something we want to protect.
وقد يكون لدينا شيئًا نود أن نحميه.
The second is we need new models and accountability systems
ثانيًا نحن بحاجة إلى إيجاد نماذج ونظام مساءلة جديدين
so that as the world gets better and more and more persuasive over time --
بحيث يصبح العالم أفضل وأكثر إقناعًا مع مرور الوقت،
because it's only going to get more persuasive --
لأنه سيصبح أكثر إقناعًا،
that the people in those control rooms
فقط عندما يصبح الأشخاص في غرفة التحكم
are accountable and transparent to what we want.
أكثر مسؤولية وشفافية تجاه ما نريده.
The only form of ethical persuasion that exists
الشكل الأخلاقي الوحيد الموجود للإقناع
is when the goals of the persuader
حينما يكون هدف الشخص المُقنِع
are aligned with the goals of the persuadee.
يتماشى مع أهداف الشخص المُقنَع.
And that involves questioning big things, like the business model of advertising.
وذلك يتضمن الاستعلام عن أشياء كبيرة، مثل النموذج التجاري للإعلانات.
Lastly,
أخيرًا،
we need a design renaissance,
نحن بحاجة إلى نهضة في التصميم،
because once you have this view of human nature,
لأنه بمجرد أن ترى الطبيعة البشرية،
that you can steer the timelines of a billion people --
التي تمكنك من توجيه الجداول الزمنية لمليار شخص،
just imagine, there's people who have some desire
تخيلوا أن هناك أشخاص لديهم رغبة
about what they want to do and what they want to be thinking
حول ما يريدون القيام به وما يريدون أن يفكروا فيه
and what they want to be feeling and how they want to be informed,
وما يريدون أن يشعروا به وكيف يودون أن يتم إعلامهم،
that tried to orchestrate the exact and most empowering
حيث تحاول التحكم بالسلطة المحددة والأكثر فاعلية
time-well-spent way for those timelines to happen.
للاستفادة من الوقت الذي تحدث فيه هذه الجداول الزمنية.
And that would involve two things:
وسيتضمن ذلك أمران:
one would be protecting against the timelines
الأول هو حمايتكم من الجداول الزمنية
that we don't want to be experiencing,
التي لا نريد أن تجربوها،
the thoughts that we wouldn't want to be happening,
والأفكار التي لا نريدها أن تحدث،
so that when that ding happens, not having the ding that sends us away;
لذلك عندما تسمعون الجرس، ليس الجرس الذي يشتت انتباهكم؛
and the second would be empowering us to live out the timeline that we want.
والثاني سيمكّننا من العيش في الجدول الزمني الذي نريده.
So let me give you a concrete example.
لذا اسمحوا لي أن أعطيكم مثالًا ملموسًا.
Today, let's say your friend cancels dinner on you,
اليوم، دعونا نقول أن أحد أصدقائكم قام بإلغاء العشاء،
and you are feeling a little bit lonely.
وتشعرون ببعض الوحدة.
And so what do you do in that moment?
ماذا ستفعلون في هذه اللحظة؟
You open up Facebook.
تقومون بفتح (فيسبوك).
And in that moment,
وفي هذه اللحظة،
the designers in the control room want to schedule exactly one thing,
المصممون في غرفة التحكم يريدون جدولة شيء واحد بالضبط،
which is to maximize how much time you spend on the screen.
وهو جدولة قضاء أقصى وقت ممكن على الشاشة.
Now, instead, imagine if those designers created a different timeline
الآن، بدلًا من ذلك، تخيلوا لو أنشأ المصممون جدول زمني مختلف
that was the easiest way, using all of their data,
والتي كانت أسهل طريقة، مستخدمين كافة بياناتهم،
to actually help you get out with the people that you care about?
لمساعدتكم على الخروج مع الأشخاص الذين تهتموا لأمرهم؟
Just think, alleviating all loneliness in society,
فكروا فقط في تخفيف العزلة في المجتمع،
if that was the timeline that Facebook wanted to make possible for people.
إذا كان ذلك هو الجدول الزمني الذي يتيحه (فيسبوك) للجميع.
Or imagine a different conversation.
أو تخيلوا محادثة أخرى.
Let's say you wanted to post something supercontroversial on Facebook,
دعونا ندّعي أنكم تريدون كتابة شيء مثير للجدل للغاية على (فيسبوك)،
which is a really important thing to be able to do,
والذي يعد مهمًا للغاية لتفعلوه،
to talk about controversial topics.
وتشاركوا موضوعات مثيرة للجدل.
And right now, when there's that big comment box,
وحاليًا يوجد هناك مربع كبير للتعليقات،
it's almost asking you, what key do you want to type?
ويسألكم تقريبًا، ما الحرف الذي تريد كتابته؟
In other words, it's scheduling a little timeline of things
بمعنى آخر، يجدول إطار زمني قليل للأشياء
you're going to continue to do on the screen.
التي ستستمرون في فعلها على الشاشة.
And imagine instead that there was another button there saying,
وتخيلوا لو أن هناك زر آخر يقول،
what would be most time well spent for you?
ما الوقت الذي تود تمضيته أكثر؟
And you click "host a dinner."
وتضغطون على "استضافة عشاء."
And right there underneath the item it said,
وهناك تحت ذلك البند تجد مكتوبًا،
"Who wants to RSVP for the dinner?"
"من تود استضافته على العشاء؟"
And so you'd still have a conversation about something controversial,
وسوف تحصلون على محادثة عن أمور مثيرة للجدل،
but you'd be having it in the most empowering place on your timeline,
ولكنها ستحدث في أكثر الأماكن تحت سلطتكم في جدولكم الزمني،
which would be at home that night with a bunch of a friends over
والذي سيكون في المنزل تلك الليلة مع مجموعة من الأصدقاء
to talk about it.
للحديث عن ذلك.
So imagine we're running, like, a find and replace
تخيل أننا ندير، مثلًا، إيجاد واستبدال
on all of the timelines that are currently steering us
جميع الجداول الزمنية التي توجهنا حاليًا
towards more and more screen time persuasively
لقضاء وقت أكثر على الشاشة بصورة مقنِعة
and replacing all of those timelines
واستبدال جميع هذه الجداول الزمنية
with what do we want in our lives.
بالأمور التي نريدها في حياتنا.
It doesn't have to be this way.
ليس من الضروري أن تكون الأمور هكذا.
Instead of handicapping our attention,
بدلًا من إعاقة اهتماماتنا،
imagine if we used all of this data and all of this power
تخيلوا لو أننا استخدمنا كافة هذه البيانات والقوة
and this new view of human nature
وهذه النظرة للطبيعة البشرية
to give us a superhuman ability to focus
لإعطائنا قدرة خارقة على التركيز
and a superhuman ability to put our attention to what we cared about
وقدرة خارقة لوضع اهتماماتنا للأمور التي تهمنا
and a superhuman ability to have the conversations
وقدرة خارقة لإجراء الحوارات
that we need to have for democracy.
التي نحتاجها من أجل الديمقراطية.
The most complex challenges in the world
التحديات الأكثر تعقيدًا في العالم
require not just us to use our attention individually.
لا تتطلب فقط استخدام اهتماماتنا فرديًا.
They require us to use our attention and coordinate it together.
ولكنها تتطلب استخدام اهتماماتنا وتنسيقها سويًا.
Climate change is going to require that a lot of people
يتطلب تغير المناخ أن يقوم العديد من الأشخاص
are being able to coordinate their attention
أن يكونوا قادرين على تنسيق اهتماماتهم
in the most empowering way together.
في أكثر الطرق تمكينًا معًا.
And imagine creating a superhuman ability to do that.
وتخيلوا إيجاد قوة خارقة لفعل ذلك.
Sometimes the world's most pressing and important problems
أحيانًا تكون أكثر المشاكل الملحة وأهمها
are not these hypothetical future things that we could create in the future.
لا تتعلق بالمستقبل الافتراضي وما يمكننا اختراعه في المستقبل.
Sometimes the most pressing problems
أحيانًا أكثر المشاكل الملحة
are the ones that are right underneath our noses,
تكون تحت مرأى ومسمع منا،
the things that are already directing a billion people's thoughts.
الأشياء التي تحدد بالفعل أفكار مليارات الناس.
And maybe instead of getting excited about the new augmented reality
وربما عوضًا عن الشعور بالحماس تجاه الواقع المدمَج الجديد
and virtual reality and these cool things that could happen,
والواقع الافتراضي وهذه الأشياء الجذابة التي قد تحدث،
which are going to be susceptible to the same race for attention,
والتي ستكون عرضة لنفس السباق نحو جذب الاهتمام،
if we could fix the race for attention
إذا استطعنا معالجة سباق جذب الاهتمام
on the thing that's already in a billion people's pockets.
حول الأشياء الموجودة بالفعل لدى مليارات الناس.
Maybe instead of getting excited
ربما بدلًا من الشعور بالحماس
about the most exciting new cool fancy education apps,
تجاه التطبيقات التعليمية الجديدة والرائعة،
we could fix the way kids' minds are getting manipulated
سيمكننا إصلاح الطرق التي تتلاعب بعقول الصغار
into sending empty messages back and forth.
نحو إرسال رسائل فارغة منهم وإليهم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Maybe instead of worrying
وبدلًا من الشعور بالقلق
about hypothetical future runaway artificial intelligences
حول المستقبل الافتراضي والذكاء الاصطناعي الجامح
that are maximizing for one goal,
الذي يصل لأقصى درجاته لتحقيق هدف واحد،
we could solve the runaway artificial intelligence
نستطيع معالجة الذكاء الاصطناعي الجامح
that already exists right now,
الذي يتواجد بالفعل الآن،
which are these newsfeeds maximizing for one thing.
التي تعمل على زيادة المتابعات الإخبارية لأقصى حد لغرض واحد.
It's almost like instead of running away to colonize new planets,
وبدلًا من الذهاب لاستعمار كواكب جديدة،
we could fix the one that we're already on.
نستطيع إصلاح الكوكب الذي نحن عليه بالفعل.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Solving this problem
إيجاد حل لهذه المشكلة
is critical infrastructure for solving every other problem.
يعد أمرًا أساسيًا لحل كل المشكلات الأخرى.
There's nothing in your life or in our collective problems
لا يوجد شيء في الحياة أو في مشكلاتنا العامة
that does not require our ability to put our attention where we care about.
لا يتطلب قدرتنا على وضع اهتمامنا في المكان الصحيح.
At the end of our lives,
وعندما تنتهي حياتنا،
all we have is our attention and our time.
نجد أن كل ما نمتلكه هو اهتمامنا ووقتنا.
What will be time well spent for ours?
ما هو الوقت الذي تود تمضيته جيدًا؟
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Tristan, thank you. Hey, stay up here a sec.
كريس أندرسون: شكرًا لك (تريستان). مهلًا، قف هنا لحظة.
First of all, thank you.
أولًا، شكرًا لك.
I know we asked you to do this talk on pretty short notice,
أعرف أننا طلبنا منك إلقاء هذه المحادثة في وقت قصير،
and you've had quite a stressful week
ومررت بأسبوع يملؤه التوتر نوعًا ما
getting this thing together, so thank you.
لجمع هذا الموضوع، لذا شكرًا لك.
Some people listening might say, what you complain about is addiction,
قد يقول بعض من استمعوك أن ما تشتكى منه هو الإدمان،
and all these people doing this stuff, for them it's actually interesting.
وكل هؤلاء الناس يفعلون هذه الأشياء، بالنسبة لهم هذا بالفعل مثير للاهتمام.
All these design decisions
كل هذه القرارات المتخذة
have built user content that is fantastically interesting.
عملت على بناء محتوى المستخدِم لتكون مثيرة جدًا.
The world's more interesting than it ever has been.
يبدو العالم أكثر إثارة مما كان عليه يومًا.
What's wrong with that?
ما عيب ذلك؟
Tristan Harris: I think it's really interesting.
(هاريس): أعتقد أن هذا مثير بالفعل.
you want to always show the more interesting next video.
فأنت تريد دومًا إظهار الفيديو التالي الأكثر إثارة.
You want to get better and better at suggesting that next video,
تريد أن تصبح أفضل وأفضل عند اقتراح هذا الفيديو التالي،
but even if you could propose the perfect next video
لكن إذا عرضت الفيديو التالي المثالي
that everyone would want to watch,
الذي يريد الجميع مشاهدته،
it would just be better and better at keeping you hooked on the screen.
فسيكون أفضل وأفضل في إبقائك متعلقًا بالشاشة.
You would want YouTube to know something about, say, falling asleep.
تريد (يوتيوب) أن تعرف شيئًا عن النوم.
"our biggest competitors are Facebook, YouTube and sleep."
"أحد أكبر منافسينا هم (فيسبوك) و(يوتيوب) والنوم."
And so what we need to recognize is that the human architecture is limited
وما نريد إدراكه هو أن البنية البشرية محدودة
and that we have certain boundaries or dimensions of our lives
وأن لدينا حدود أو أبعاد معينة لحياتنا
that we want to be honored and respected,
نريد بها أن نشعر بالتكريم والاحترام
and technology could help do that.
وتستطيع التكنولوجيا المساعدة في ذلك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
CA: I mean, could you make the case
كريس أندرسون: هل تستطيع توضيح الوضع
that part of the problem here is that we've got a naïve model of human nature?
حيث يكون جزء من المشكلة أننا لدينا نموذج ساذج عن الطبيعة البشرية؟
So much of this is justified in terms of human preference,
ويبرَّر معظم هذا من ناحية التفضيلات البشرية،
where we've got these algorithms that do an amazing job
حيث يكون لدينا هذه الخوارزميات التي تقوم بعمل رائع
of optimizing for human preference,
في الاستفادة من التفضيلات البشرية،
but which preference?
لكن أي نوع من التفضيلات؟
There's the preferences of things that we really care about
هناك التفضيلات عن الأشياء التي تهمنا
when we think about them
عندما نفكر فيها
versus the preferences of what we just instinctively click on.
في مقابل التفضيلات التي نضغط عليها غريزيًا.
If we could implant that more nuanced view of human nature in every design,
إذا استطعنا زرع وجهة النظر الدقيقة عن الطبيعة البشرية في كل تصميم،
would that be a step forward?
هل سيكون هذا خطوة للأمام؟
TH: Absolutely. I mean, I think right now
(هاريس): بالتأكيد، أعني أنني أعتقد الآن
it's as if all of our technology is basically only asking our lizard brain
كما لو كانت التكنولوجيا الخاصة بنا تستحضر أساسًا عقل السحلية خاصتنا
what's the best way to just impulsively get you to do
ما أفضل طريقة تجعلك تقوم بشكل متهور
the next tiniest thing with your time,
بالشيء التالي الصغير لقضاء وقتك،
instead of asking you in your life
بدلًا من سؤالك عن حياتك
what we would be most time well spent for you?
ما الوقت الذي تود تمضيته أكثر؟
What would be the perfect timeline that might include something later,
ما هو أفضل جدول زمني الذي قد يتضمن شيئًا فيما بعد،
would be time well spent for you here at TED in your last day here?
هل سيكون الوقت الذي تمضيه في (TED) في يومك الأخير هنا؟
CA: So if Facebook and Google and everyone said to us first up,
(سي ايه): إذا قال لنا (فيسبوك) و(جوجل) وغيرهما في البداية،
"Hey, would you like us to optimize for your reflective brain
"مرحبًا، هل تودون منا أن نحسّن عقلكم التأملي
or your lizard brain? You choose."
أو عقل السحلية لديكم؟ الاختيار لكم."
TH: Right. That would be one way. Yes.
(هاريس): هذه إحدى الطرق. نعم.
CA: You said persuadability, that's an interesting word to me
(سي ايه): ذكرت كلمة "قابلية الإقناع" هذه مثيرة لاهتمامي
because to me there's two different types of persuadability.
لأنه يوجد نوعين مختلفين منها.
There's the persuadability that we're trying right now
هناك إقناع الذي نحاول القيام به الآن
but I think you're almost talking about a different kind,
لكني أعتقد أنك تتحدث تقريبًا عن نوع مختلف،
a more visceral type of persuadability,
نوعًا من الإقتاع أكثر شبابًا وعفوية،
of being persuaded without even knowing that you're thinking.
لأن الشخص يقتنع بدون حتى معرفة أنه يفكر.
that taught [students how to recognize] exactly these techniques.
ويعلم الطلاب كيفية تحديد هذه التقنيات.
There's conferences and workshops that teach people all these covert ways
هناك مؤتمرات وورش عمل توضح للناس كل هذه الطرق الخفية
of getting people's attention and orchestrating people's lives.
للحصول على انتباه الناس والتحكم بحياتهم.
And it's because most people don't know that that exists
ولأن معظم الناس لا يعلمون بوجود هذا
that this conversation is so important.
فتمثل هذه المحادثة أهمية كبيرة.
CA: Tristan, you and I, we both know so many people from all these companies.
(سي إيه): نعلم كلانا الكثير من الناس في هذه الشركات.
There are actually many here in the room,
هناك في الواقع العديد منهم في القاعة،
and I don't know about you, but my experience of them
ولا أعلم رأيك، لكن انطباعي عنهم
is that there is no shortage of good intent.
أنه لا تنقص لديهم النية الحسنة.
People want a better world.
يريد الناس عالمًا أفضل.
They are actually -- they really want it.
هم بالفعل يريدون ذلك.
And I don't think anything you're saying is that these are evil people.
ولا أعتقد أنك أوحيت بكلامك أنهم أشرار.
It's a system where there's these unintended consequences
إنه نظام حيث تقبع فيه هذه العواقب غير المقصودة
that have really got out of control --
التي خرجت عن السيطرة،
TH: Of this race for attention.
(هاريس): عن هذا السباق نحو الاهتمام.
It's the classic race to the bottom when you have to get attention,
هذا سباق قديم نحو الحضيض عندما تضطر إلى الحصول على الانتباه،
and it's so tense.
ويتسم بالتوتر الشديد.
The only way to get more is to go lower on the brain stem,
الطريق الوحيد للحصول على المزيد هو أن تتعمق داخل الدماغ،
to go lower into outrage, to go lower into emotion,
تتعمق لتحصل على الغضب والعاطفة،
to go lower into the lizard brain.
تتعمق لتصل لعقل السحلية.
CA: Well, thank you so much for helping us all get a little bit wiser about this.
(سي إيه): حسنًا، شكرًا جزيلًا لمساعدتنا على أن نصبح حكماء أكثر بشأن هذا.
Tristan Harris, thank you. TH: Thank you very much.
(هاريس): شكرًا. شكرًا جزيلًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)